<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[timmesserschmidt]]></title>
  <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-18T16:54:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Messerschmidt]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summary Google I/O 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/18/summary-google-io-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-18T10:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/18/summary-google-io-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday this year&#8217;s Google I/O officially ended with a series of Code Labs, Fireside Chats and talks about more general techniques. For me it was the second I/O in a row and I&#8217;ll try to briefly summarize the event in this post.</p>

<h2>Day 0 - Tuesday</h2>

<p>At about 2pm people can check-in at the Moscone Center to get their badge (and their shirt). For me this day is great because you meet lots of old friends in the line waiting in front of the Moscone Center or inside after having checked-in.</p>

<p>Nothing really special happens here but you can clearly see that everybody is super-excited about the day after.</p>

<p><strong>Facebook Developer Party:</strong><br/>
A meet-up with tons of I/O attendees. It was next to the Moscone Center at <a href="http://www.jillianssf.com/">Jillian&#8217;s</a>. I had good food and some nice talks but left early to meet some colleagues from our San Jose office.</p>

<h2>Day 1 - Wednesday</h2>

<p>For me this day started at 7am standing in the line of people that wants to get into the Moscone. Google serves some breakfast (not the best, not the worst) and people queue up inside in front of the escalators that get you on the 2nd level of Moscone. Basically this means 1 hour of standing in a queue, chatting with old &amp; new friends and getting super excited about what&#8217;s being announced at the Keynote.</p>

<p>At 8:15am they finally opened up the escalators and the crowd is running (yes, running) up to the 2nd level where they have to wait again for a bit. Then at 8:30am people are allowed to use the escalators to the 3rd and final level of Moscone. Basically everybody runs into the big room to get a decent seat that let&#8217;s you enjoy the Keynote. There is really that much people that some of them have to stand outside and have to use the monitors to watch what happens on stage.</p>

<p><strong>The Keynote:</strong>  After some fancy music &amp; visualizations finally the Keynote starts and people like Hugo Barra, Vic Gundotra and even Larry Page enter the stage.</p>

<p>The big announcements were not as big as last year. This year&#8217;s theme seemed to be <em>evolution instead of revolution</em>. Google Maps became a nice update and finally looks fancy on all platforms (even the iPad - yay). Google Music becomes All Access and offers streaming of music similar to Spotify (US credit cards only - not so yay). Android&#8217;s Play Services become a serious foundation of Android by bringing lots of new services like Google&#8217;s Gaming Service to Android. Furthermore really interesting features for location are now accessible for developers on all important API levels. They presented a Samsung Galaxy S4 running stock Android 4.2.2 (but didn&#8217;t give it away). You could clearly see that Google get&#8217;s the ecosystem to play after their rules and behave nicely.</p>

<p>The often critized Android Developer Console (that&#8217;s where you upload your apps for the Google Play Store) got a total revamp and offers finally lots of really good features. Developer can upload Alpha and Beta versions of their apps and get some interesting statistics. Additionally they can use a staged rollout to distribute new versions of their app in a more controlled way. <em>All</em> developers are now able to reply to comments on the Play Store and much more really useful things like inbuilt translation services (paid).</p>

<p><strong>BUT:</strong> They didn&#8217;t announce a new version of Android. It seems like they wanted to wait with 4.3 or 5.0 - or whatever it will be called - until it&#8217;s really ready for rollout (which I support).</p>

<p>The real <em>big</em> focus this year was Chrome. Google highlighted a lot of interesting features like Google Now for Chrome and gave away a Chromebook Pixel to every attendee. Google wants to make sure to push the web as much as they pushed Android before. Therefore they announced Web Components which serve as bits and pieces to build your own web app. Furthermore they introduced an interesting <em>PayPal-like</em> Google Wallet feature that allows for auto-completing checkout forms.</p>

<p>Google+ got some big updates, too: The UI got redisgned and looks now very sleek. They basically used the nice mobile layout and made it desktop friendly by allowing multiple columns with big focus on media like pictures. Additionally they reworked the photos. Uploaded pictures are being enhanced to produce optimum quality. I tried this functionality with a few different pictures and liked it so far. Furthermore there was a heavy focus on Google+ Sign-in for all platforms. The most kick-ass feature is the <em>Over The Air Install</em>-feature that allows to install an app and automatically login on your Android device after logging in on the associated website.</p>

<p>A very pleasant thing is the big focus of Google on education. As an example they opened up an Android store for schools &amp; universities that allows teachers to purchase apps for their whole class.</p>

<p>The Keynote was being ended by Larry Page coming up on stage (first time since a very loooong time) and talking about the important role of technology for education, Google&#8217;s focus for the next few years and much more. After his really moving talk he accepted some questions from the audience and tried to answer them as good as possible.</p>

<p>The only person I missed was Sergey Brin. Last year he took over a big part of the Keynote by having people jumping out of an airplane using Google Glass and this year he just wasn&#8217;t there. The Keynote&#8217;s speed &amp; rhythm was very different compared to last year&#8217;s. This didn&#8217;t make it any better or worse.</p>

<p><strong>After the Keynote:</strong> I met tons of people, walked through the Sandboxes and tried a lot of new hardware. Google did a very interesting selection with products like <a href="http://www.leapmotion.com/">Leap Motion</a> or <a href="http://www.oculusvr.com/">Oculus Rift</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Sessions attended:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>What&#8217;s new in Android Developer Tools</li>
<li>An Introduction to Integrating Google+ Sign-in</li>
<li>Writing Custom Views for Android</li>
<li>Volley: Easy, Fast Networking for Android</li>
<li>In-App Billing Version 3</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>The After Hours Party:</strong> Robots, Drinks, Food &amp; Billy Idol. What more can I say? This was amazing. People expected <em>Daft Punk</em> to be there, too - due to a lot of mentiones during the keynote and <em>Get Lucky</em> being played everywhere - but this year the electric part was taken over by a guy called <em>Steve Aoki</em>.</p>

<h2>Day 2 - Thursday</h2>

<p>This year&#8217;s second day didn&#8217;t bring another Keynote. This day was very much focussed on sessions &amp; Fireside Chats instead. One of the main topics this day was <em>Google Glass</em>. Funnily it didn&#8217;t really even get mentioned during Wednesday&#8217;s Keynote.</p>

<p><strong>Sessions attended:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Developing For Glass</li>
<li>Building Glass Services with the Google Mirror API</li>
<li>Voiding Your Warranty: Hacking Glass</li>
<li>Fireside Chat with the Glass Team</li>
<li>Fireside Chat with the Android Team</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Google I/O Nightcap:</strong> This was a fun event in the evening at <a href="http://www.thirstybear.com/">Thirsty Bear Brewery</a> where I met lots of GDG people, had a few drinks and good food. Sadly the event closed at 10pm.</p>

<h2>Day 3 - Friday</h2>

<p>This day is the &#8220;saying goodbye&#8221;-day. Lots of people have already left San Francisco to leave for their hometowns.</p>

<p><strong>Sessions attended:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>The New Android SDK Build System</li>
<li>What&#8217;s new for Developers in Google Play</li>
<li>Android Design in Action</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bottom line:</h2>

<p>As last year&#8217;s I/O this year was very special. There is not lots of conferences where you meet top-notch developers like at this event. Not wearing Glass made you feel bad (due to the <em>high</em> concentration of people wearing it) and not too many details about the plans for Glass were shared. Still nobody knows when &amp; if Glass is coming to Europe and how to enroll for the next wave of trials. Google made this event special and I&#8217;m sure that next I/O will rock, too.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll have to take the time to watch the recorded sessions that I couldn&#8217;t attend due to clashs or just because the audience was that big that you couldn&#8217;t get into the room (happened a few times to me).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress Alfred Workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/11/octopress-alfred-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-11T10:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/11/octopress-alfred-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is just a very short post highlighting a very nice Alfred workflow that adds support for creating new posts for Octopress or regenerating the site. Furthermore I&#8217;ll quickly describe how I post my stuff to GitHub.</p>

<p>You can find the workflow over <a href="http://www.alfredforum.com/topic/2289-octopress-publisher/">at the Alfred forums</a> or <a href="https://github.com/Temikus/alfred-octopress/">at GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>To me this is very useful since I don&#8217;t need to open iTerm first, navigate to my blog&#8217;s folder, create a new file using rake and open the file in vi(m) or <a href="http://mouapp.com/">Mou</a>.</p>

<p>This is my Git workflow to test the blog locally and add new posts:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>alias octopush='git push origin source && rake generate && rake deploy'
</span><span class='line'>alias octoprev='rake generate && rake preview'</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Place that into your .zshrc or .bashrc or whatever you use and you only have to do the following before:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>git add .
</span><span class='line'>git commit -am "My fancy message"</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Basically I test before commiting with <code>octoprev</code> and use <code>octopush</code> afterwards to push to GitHub.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's in your bag?]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/whats-in-your-bag/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T17:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/whats-in-your-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things I do a lot working as Developer Evangelist is traveling. Flying from Berlin to Amsterdam, Amsterdam to London and back to Berlin. From Berlin to Vilnius and from Vilnius to Stockholm and back. And so on and so on and so on. When I meet people who travel as much as I do one of the big topic is mostly organizing and optimizing travels. Especially: What do you take with you when traveling? This post tries to highlight some key important things to me when traveling light (for max 2 days), medium (2 to 5 days) or heavy (5 days and above).</p>

<h2>Traveling light</h2>

<p>Traveling light is from the baggage perspective my most favorite thing to do. The reason why: I don&#8217;t get to carry around to much stuff when being at the airport, getting to the hotel using public transport or a cab or being at events.</p>

<p>The key element for this is my backpack. It&#8217;s a Dakine that&#8217;s already a few years old (about 5 or 6?!) and does everything I need when traveling. It has a special padded pocket for my Mac, one for glasses (which I misuse for business cards), one for keys and documents and which is designed to keep stuff cool but I misuse it for chargers, cables and adapters.</p>

<p>What do I take with me when traveling light?</p>

<ul>
<li>MacBook Pro, 15&#8221; (Late 2012) with 8GB Ram and a Core i7 @ 2.4 GHz</li>
<li>iPhone 4S (Company phone)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lightning-Thunderbolt-Blackberry-connectors-customized/dp/B009USAJCC">Anker Mobile Battery</a> which charges up my phone about 4-5 times</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sanyo-eneloop-KBC-L2B-Mobile-Booster/dp/B004BQJXJI">Sanyo Mobile Booster</a> - another battery (tinier) that charges up my phone about 2-3 times</li>
<li>Sunglasses (if it makes sense - sadly I almost always forget them)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bose%C2%AE-QuietComfort%C2%AE-Acoustic-Cancelling%C2%AE-Headphones/dp/B0054JJ0QW">Bose QC15 Noise Cancelling Headset</a> - helps to actually be productive at airports.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/AKG-Acoustics-K375-Headphone-Black/dp/B00A1UHM1Y">AKG K375</a> In-ear headphone - more mobile than the Bose and doesn&#8217;t require battery</li>
<li>Lots of different cables (iPhone / iPad cable, USB, &#8230;)</li>
<li>Dextro Energy (dextrose) - to get some energy in</li>
<li>A small notebook and a pen</li>
</ul>


<p>When not traveling in Europe I always take with me:
- Country-specific Mac adaptors (I bought the travel-kit once)
- <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Charger-Designed-Quality-Blackberrys-Countries/dp/B002G90I3M">A Skross World Adapter</a> with 2 USB connectors
- Passport (useful also in UK)</p>

<h2>Traveling medium</h2>

<p>Traveling medium is needed if I get to stay for a bit longer at one event or I need to connect them because traveling back to Berlin to get new stuff doesn&#8217;t make sense.</p>

<p>In this case I need to get both my backpack and a tiny suitcase (which has the optimum size for handluggage). Basically I put everything inside my backpack that I mentioned above already PLUS more clothes and additionally this tech:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Razer-Mobile-Gaming-Speakers-RZ05-00500100-R3/dp/B004L2JPS6">Razer Ferox speakers</a> (charged via USB) that spice up listening to Music / watching movies in the hotel</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Apple-AirPort-Express-Station-MC414LL/dp/B008ALA2RC/">Apple Airport Express</a> for connecting to the hotel&#8217;s LAN and having a real good WiFi</li>
<li>LAN cable (to connect the Airport Express to the room&#8217;s LAN port)</li>
<li>iPad 3 32GB wih 3G (for gaming and reading stuff)</li>
<li>Kindle Paperwhite (reading stuff, again)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Traveling heavy</h2>

<p>Traveling heavy replaces the tiny suitcase by a big one (that can contain enough stuff for two weeks).</p>

<p>So this happens when I travel over to the US or do marathon events like Mobile World Congress or LeWeb with lots of satellite events around the event itself. This only happens a few times (&lt; 10) a year. This is when I bring more stuff to develop with.</p>

<ul>
<li>Nexus 4 16GB</li>
<li>Nexus 7 16GB</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Logitech-Wireless-Gaming-Mouse-G700/dp/B003VAM32E">Logitech G700 Mouse</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>When having a presentation</h2>

<p>I&#8217;ve got a tiny bag that sits in my backpack and contains:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Logitech-910-001354-Wireless-Presenter-R400/dp/B002GHBUTK">Logitech R400</a></li>
<li>Display Adapter VGA</li>
<li>Display Adapter DVI</li>
<li>Display Adapter HDMI</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bottom line</h2>

<p>I&#8217;m very happy with discussing my &#8216;setup&#8217; and even receive some new ideas that could enhance my gear. The new stuff that I look into buying might be a better iPad Mini (Apple: Please release an iPad Mini with a Retina Display) and a MacBook Air 13&#8221; (because my Pro is sooo damn heavy).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summary AngelHack Berlin 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/summary-angelhack-berlin-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T14:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/summary-angelhack-berlin-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last weekend the famous <a href="http://angelhack.com/">AngelHack</a> came to Berlin to find the best local hackers. The winning teams are going to be mentored for 3 months and will be shipped over to the US afterwards to raise investments, meet VCs etc. in the Valley.</p>

<p><img class="no-box center" src="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/images/posts/angelhack.png" title="AngelHack" ></p>

<p>This years winner was <a href="http://www.hackathon.io/edgar">edgar</a> - a beautiful product that tries to help small medium business that are not as Internet-oriented as others to build an online presence for their product and tell the story behind them.</p>

<p>Winner of the PayPal category was a product called <a href="http://travelo.me/">travelo.me</a>. travelo aims at people that are upset with the difficulty of planning (private) trips. It optimizes routes between sights and proposes new landmarks that might be of interest for you.</p>

<h2>What I liked:</h2>

<ul>
<li>The teams were really international - I met lots of people coming from other cities or even countries</li>
<li>There were a lot of people in the AngelHack team trying to help participants, speakers and sponsors (thanks!)</li>
<li>The organizer tried to get the &#8216;spirit&#8217; of AngelHack to Berlin</li>
<li>Lots of projects (I counted 30) and a good amount of hackers (~ 140)</li>
<li>The jury consisted of a good mixture (startups, developers, business)</li>
<li>Enough cold drinks (especially Club Mate)</li>
</ul>


<h2>What I didn&#8217;t like:</h2>

<ul>
<li>The WiFi at the Immobilien Scout Office was too slow since not being dimensioned for ~ 140 developers</li>
<li>There was a shortage of food (at least on the first day)</li>
<li>The location didn&#8217;t have enough power outlets for the teams (especially applies to the Scout Casino)</li>
<li>There was no desk for the presenters - thus live coding was nearly impossible</li>
<li>There was no handsfree mic for the presenters - thus live coding was nearly impossible</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bottom line:</h2>

<p>The first AngelHack in Berlin was good. For the next time I&#8217;d love to see some of the dislikes being addressed. There is lots of potential for professional (&amp; even paid) hackathons in Germany and especially in Berlin.</p>

<h2>Thanks:</h2>

<p>Thanks to the team around <a href="http://www.youisnow.de/">YouIsNow</a> that managed the whole hack and a special thanks to the team of <a href="http://mailjet.com">Mailjet</a> and <a href="http://www.paymill.com">Paymill</a> for a nice weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A new start using Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/a-new-start-using-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T11:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/a-new-start-using-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I&#8217;ve spent some time <a href="http://timmesserschmidt.blogspot.com">blogging on Blogger</a> I wanted to try something new. The reason for that is not necessarily Blogger not being a good platform for your blog but me being eager to learn new stuff.</p>

<p>Having <a href="http://battlehack.org">worked with Jekyll before</a> it was pretty obvious to me that I wanted to go for a solution that allows me to configure my blog and adds some pretty cool functionality like nicely formatted code embeds, writing posts in Markdown and of course deploying my site to GitHub pages. I could have either used Jekyll itself (<a href="http://blog.parkermoore.de/2013/05/06/jekyll-1-dot-0-released/">which just got bumped to version 1.0</a>) or used Octopress (which I do).</p>

<p>The reason I stick with Octopress is that it comes with a decent default theme (which I&#8217;ll tweak over time) and does a lot of configuration / JS /  … that Jekyll still requires to be done manually.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll be blogging mainly about my life as Developer Evangelist, summarizing events I&#8217;ve been at and linking to interesting content I&#8217;ve found. Additionally I&#8217;ll be covering tools / apps / etc. that I like a lot and help me with being productive.</p>

<p>The reason I&#8217;m not importing stuff is that my old blog was a mess of both German and English posts and I didn&#8217;t really have a straight idea about what the content should be like.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
