<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[timmesserschmidt]]></title>
  <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-07T07:26:46+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Messerschmidt]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summary AngelHack Berlin 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/summary-angelhack-berlin-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T14:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/summary-angelhack-berlin-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last weekend the famous <a href="http://angelhack.com/">AngelHack</a> came to Berlin to find the best local hackers. The winning teams are going to be mentored for 3 months and will be shipped over to the US afterwards to raise investments, meet VCs etc. in the Valley.</p>

<p><img class="no-box center" src="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/images/posts/angelhack.png" title="AngelHack" ></p>

<p>This years winner was <a href="http://www.hackathon.io/edgar">edgar</a> - a beautiful product that tries to help small medium business that are not as Internet-oriented as others to build an online presence for their product and tell the story behind them.</p>

<p>Winner of the PayPal category was a product called <a href="http://travelo.me/">travelo.me</a>. travelo aims at people that are upset with the difficulty of planning (private) trips. It optimizes routes between sights and proposes new landmarks that might be of interest for you.</p>

<h2>What I liked:</h2>

<ul>
<li>The teams were really international - I met lots of people coming from other cities or even countries</li>
<li>There were a lot of people in the AngelHack team trying to help participants, speakers and sponsors (thanks!)</li>
<li>The organizer tried to get the &#8216;spirit&#8217; of AngelHack to Berlin</li>
<li>Lots of projects (I counted 30) and a good amount of hackers (~ 140)</li>
<li>The jury consisted of a good mixture (startups, developers, business)</li>
<li>Enough cold drinks (especially Club Mate)</li>
</ul>


<h2>What I didn&#8217;t like:</h2>

<ul>
<li>The WiFi at the Immobilien Scout Office was too slow since not being dimensioned for ~ 140 developers</li>
<li>There was a shortage of food (at least on the first day)</li>
<li>The location didn&#8217;t have enough power outlets for the teams (especially applies to the Scout Casino)</li>
<li>There was no desk for the presenters - thus live coding was nearly impossible</li>
<li>There was no handsfree mic for the presenters - thus live coding was nearly impossible</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bottom line:</h2>

<p>The first AngelHack in Berlin was good. For the next time I&#8217;d love to see some of the dislikes being addressed. There is lots of potential for professional (&amp; even paid) hackathons in Germany and especially in Berlin.</p>

<h2>Thanks:</h2>

<p>Thanks to the team around <a href="http://www.youisnow.de/">YouIsNow</a> that managed the whole hack and a special thanks to the team of <a href="http://mailjet.com">Mailjet</a> and <a href="http://www.paymill.com">Paymill</a> for a nice weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A new start using Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/a-new-start-using-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-06T11:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/06/a-new-start-using-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I&#8217;ve spent some time <a href="http://timmesserschmidt.blogspot.com">blogging on Blogger</a> I wanted to try something new. The reason for that is not necessarily Blogger not being a good platform for your blog but me being eager to learn new stuff.</p>

<p>Having <a href="http://battlehack.org">worked with Jekyll before</a> it was pretty obvious to me that I wanted to go for a solution that allows me to configure my blog and adds some pretty cool functionality like nicely formatted code embeds, writing posts in Markdown and of course deploying my site to GitHub pages. I could have either used Jekyll itself (<a href="http://blog.parkermoore.de/2013/05/06/jekyll-1-dot-0-released/">which just got bumped to version 1.0</a>) or used Octopress (which I do).</p>

<p>The reason I stick with Octopress is that it comes with a decent default theme (which I&#8217;ll tweak over time) and does a lot of configuration / JS /  … that Jekyll still requires to be done manually.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll be blogging mainly about my life as Developer Evangelist, summarizing events I&#8217;ve been at and linking to interesting content I&#8217;ve found. Additionally I&#8217;ll be covering tools / apps / etc. that I like a lot and help me with being productive.</p>

<p>The reason I&#8217;m not importing stuff is that my old blog was a mess of both German and English posts and I didn&#8217;t really have a straight idea about what the content should be like.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
