<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Travel | timmesserschmidt]]></title>
  <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-18T17:11:49-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Messerschmidt]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's in your bag?]]></title>
    <link href="http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/whats-in-your-bag/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T17:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://seraphimserapis.github.io/blog/2013/05/08/whats-in-your-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things I do a lot working as Developer Evangelist is traveling. Flying from Berlin to Amsterdam, Amsterdam to London and back to Berlin. From Berlin to Vilnius and from Vilnius to Stockholm and back. And so on and so on and so on. When I meet people who travel as much as I do one of the big topic is mostly organizing and optimizing travels. Especially: What do you take with you when traveling? This post tries to highlight some key important things to me when traveling light (for max 2 days), medium (2 to 5 days) or heavy (5 days and above).</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Traveling light</h2>

<p>Traveling light is from the baggage perspective my most favorite thing to do. The reason why: I don't get to carry around to much stuff when being at the airport, getting to the hotel using public transport or a cab or being at events.</p>

<p>The key element for this is my backpack. It's a Dakine that's already a few years old (about 5 or 6?!) and does everything I need when traveling. It has a special padded pocket for my Mac, one for glasses (which I misuse for business cards), one for keys and documents and which is designed to keep stuff cool but I misuse it for chargers, cables and adapters.</p>

<p>What do I take with me when traveling light?</p>

<ul>
<li>MacBook Pro, 15" (Late 2012) with 8GB Ram and a Core i7 @ 2.4 GHz</li>
<li>iPhone 4S (Company phone)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lightning-Thunderbolt-Blackberry-connectors-customized/dp/B009USAJCC">Anker Mobile Battery</a> which charges up my phone about 4-5 times</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sanyo-eneloop-KBC-L2B-Mobile-Booster/dp/B004BQJXJI">Sanyo Mobile Booster</a> - another battery (tinier) that charges up my phone about 2-3 times</li>
<li>Sunglasses (if it makes sense - sadly I almost always forget them)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bose%C2%AE-QuietComfort%C2%AE-Acoustic-Cancelling%C2%AE-Headphones/dp/B0054JJ0QW">Bose QC15 Noise Cancelling Headset</a> - helps to actually be productive at airports.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/AKG-Acoustics-K375-Headphone-Black/dp/B00A1UHM1Y">AKG K375</a> In-ear headphone - more mobile than the Bose and doesn't require battery</li>
<li>Lots of different cables (iPhone / iPad cable, USB, ...)</li>
<li>Dextro Energy (dextrose) - to get some energy in</li>
<li>A small notebook and a pen</li>
</ul>


<p>When not traveling in Europe I always take with me:
- Country-specific Mac adaptors (I bought the travel-kit once)
- <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Charger-Designed-Quality-Blackberrys-Countries/dp/B002G90I3M">A Skross World Adapter</a> with 2 USB connectors
- Passport (useful also in UK)</p>

<h2>Traveling medium</h2>

<p>Traveling medium is needed if I get to stay for a bit longer at one event or I need to connect them because traveling back to Berlin to get new stuff doesn't make sense.</p>

<p>In this case I need to get both my backpack and a tiny suitcase (which has the optimum size for handluggage). Basically I put everything inside my backpack that I mentioned above already PLUS more clothes and additionally this tech:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Razer-Mobile-Gaming-Speakers-RZ05-00500100-R3/dp/B004L2JPS6">Razer Ferox speakers</a> (charged via USB) that spice up listening to Music / watching movies in the hotel</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Apple-AirPort-Express-Station-MC414LL/dp/B008ALA2RC/">Apple Airport Express</a> for connecting to the hotel's LAN and having a real good WiFi</li>
<li>LAN cable (to connect the Airport Express to the room's LAN port)</li>
<li>iPad 3 32GB wih 3G (for gaming and reading stuff)</li>
<li>Kindle Paperwhite (reading stuff, again)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Traveling heavy</h2>

<p>Traveling heavy replaces the tiny suitcase by a big one (that can contain enough stuff for two weeks).</p>

<p>So this happens when I travel over to the US or do marathon events like Mobile World Congress or LeWeb with lots of satellite events around the event itself. This only happens a few times (&lt; 10) a year. This is when I bring more stuff to develop with.</p>

<ul>
<li>Nexus 4 16GB</li>
<li>Nexus 7 16GB</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Logitech-Wireless-Gaming-Mouse-G700/dp/B003VAM32E">Logitech G700 Mouse</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>When having a presentation</h2>

<p>I've got a tiny bag that sits in my backpack and contains:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Logitech-910-001354-Wireless-Presenter-R400/dp/B002GHBUTK">Logitech R400</a></li>
<li>Display Adapter VGA</li>
<li>Display Adapter DVI</li>
<li>Display Adapter HDMI</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bottom line</h2>

<p>I'm very happy with discussing my 'setup' and even receive some new ideas that could enhance my gear. The new stuff that I look into buying might be a better iPad Mini (Apple: Please release an iPad Mini with a Retina Display) and a MacBook Air 13" (because my Pro is sooo damn heavy).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
